Guide to the Mount Vernon Seminary and College Office of Public Relations collection, 1925-1998 MVC0055.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary and College Office of Public Relations collection
circa 1925-1998
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MVC0055.RG
2.5 Linear Feet
The Mount Vernon Seminary was officially established by Elizabeth Somers in 1875 and a two year junior college was added in 1927. The Junior College remained open until 1969, when Mount Vernon College became a four-year unversity. The university was an independent institution until 1999, when it became affilated with The George Washington University. This collection includes photographs, negatives, press clippings and public relations materials from Mount Vernon Seminary and College.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: photographs and negatives, Press releases and publications, and Press clippings.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains public relations materials from Mount Vernon Seminary, Mount Vernon Junior College, and Mount Vernon College, including photographs, negatives, press releases, public relations publications, and press clippins. The material dates from 1925-1998.
Biographical / Historical
The Mount Vernon Seminary was officially established by Elizabeth Somers in 1875 with classes held at her residence on F Street; she named it after her brother's church in Baltimore, Mount Vernon Place Methodist. The Seminary began as a six year prepatory school, with four years of high school level classes, and two years of post-high school curriculum, calling it a "Family and Day School for Young Ladies." In order to graduate, students had to complete a formal process of "Senior Essays" in which they completed primary research and wrote on a current political or social topic, including such provocative issues as child labor, prohibition, poverty, and women's suffrage.
The school was moved to 1100 M. Street N.W. in 1900 and was once again moved in 1917 to a campus on Nebraska Avenue. In 1920 graduating class, eight women continued their education at universities such as the University of Wisconsin, Stanford, Northwestern and the University of Texas; by 1923 graduates were going to such other prestigious universities as UC-Berkeley, Columbia, Cornell, Smith College and the University of Chicago. Such advancements in higher education were uncommon for women of the day, but Mount Vernon was one of the premier prepatory institutions in the country.
In 1927, Mount Vernon established a Junior College, and with its establishment, students no longer had to complete six years of courses to receive a diploma; they graduated from the Seminary after four years and could continue on to the Junior College for two more years of college preparation. After World War II began, the U.S. Navy took over the campus in 1942 as a part of the war effort. During the 1943 academic year, the Seminary held classes in Spring Valley by leasing neighborhood residences. After receiving "just compensation" for their Nebraska Avneue campus, the school purchased 21 acres on Foxhall Road and surrounding areas in 1945, and had applied for accreditation to award Associates of Arts Degrees after completing two years of the Junior College.
Despite its expansion, by 1965 the Board of Trustees voted unanimously to dissolve the Seminary by 1969, as it could not financially support both institutions. During the 1960s, the Junior College developed new academic concentrations such as government, international relations and political science to reflect its location in the nation's capital. At the same time, it began to phase out its vocational training such as home economics and secretarial skills to make room for these higher education courses.
By 1973, the Board of Higher Education licensed the college to award Bachelor of Arts (BA) degrees such as Public Affairs, Government, Business Administration, Childhood, Special Education, and the Visual Arts, as well as honorary Doctor of Humane Letters and Juris Doctor Degrees; in 1976, the college received initial accreditation as a four-year college and was reaccredited ten years later. However, by 1996 the college announced a plan to affiliate with George Washington University and the last class of Mount Vernon College graduated in 1999. Today, as an affiliated campus of GWU, Mount Vernon offers special living accommodations, as well as learning and leadership programs for female students.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Mount Vernon Seminary and College archives were acquired by GWU upon merger with Mount Vernon College. The collection was transferred to the Foggy Bottom campus in 2009.
Public relations; Women's colleges; Women -- Education; Mount Vernon College; Mount Vernon Seminary
- Photographs and negatives, circa 1925-1998; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  The materials of this series include photographs and negatives of both the students and campus of Mount Vernon Seminary, Mount Vernon Junior College, and Mount Vernon College. They range in date from 1925-1998.
  - Golden Jubilee, 1925; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Foxhall Road campus life, circa 1940-1960; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Lloyd, circa 1950-1965; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Campus events--photos, circa 1960-1970; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Campus events--negatives, circa 1960-1970; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Contact sheets, circa 1960-1980; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Alumnae events/submitted photos, circa 1960-1980; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Campus events--negatives, circa 1960-1980; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Campus events--negatives, circa 1960-1980; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Campus life--negatives, circa 1960-1980; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Campus life--contact sheets, circa 1960-1980; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Campus life--contact sheets, circa 1960-1980; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Campus life--contact sheets, circa 1960-1980; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Campus life--contact sheets, circa 1960-1980; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Campus life--contact sheets, circa 1960-1980; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Peter Pelham at an unknown event, circa 1961-1977; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Florence Hollis Hand chapel construction and dedication, circa 1965-1970; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Florence Hollis Hand chapel construction and dedication, circa 1965-1970; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Florence Hollis Hand chapel construction--negatives, circa 1965-1970; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Florence Hollis Hand chapel construction--contact sheets, circa 1965-1970; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Florence Hollis Hand chapel construction--matted photos, circa 1965-1970; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Alumnae Council--negatives, 1967; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Alumnae Council--negatives, 1967; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Building Program Site Presentation Photos, 1969; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Study abroad photos (Peru) from Lynn Warthen (?), circa 1970-1979; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Students at the Capitol--contact sheets, circa 1970-1979; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Students at the Capitol--negatives, circa 1970-1979; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Campus life, circa 1970-1979; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Students in Washington, D.C., circa 1970-1980; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Campus life--slides and negatives, 1973; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Centennial celebration--contact sheets, 1975; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Centennial celebration, 1975; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Campus life, circa 1976; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Commencement 1976--contact sheets, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Unknown event--negatives, 1979; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Unknown campus event and a fallen tree on campus, circa 1980-1998; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Dr. Jane Evans's inaguration--contact sheets, 1981; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Olympic torch at Mount Vernon, 1996; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Unidentified photographs and negatives, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Press releases and publications, circa 1940-1996; Series 2
  The materials of this series include press releases and publications sent out by the public relations offices of Mount Vernon College. They range in date from 1940-1996.
  - Public relations publications and press releases, circa 1940-1970; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Public relations--Hoyt, 1974-1975; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Press releases, 1975; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Press releases, 1975-1979; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Mout Vernon College publications, 1988-1989; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Public relations brochures, library campaign, 1988-1989; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Press releases re: art exhibits, campus, concerts, 1990-1991; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Press releases re: administration, 1990-1991; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Press releases re: continuing education, commencement, convocation, courses, 1990-1991; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Press releases re: lectures, sports, students, 1990-1991; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Mount Vernon College PR material scripts, 1992; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Olympic torch celebration at Mount Vernon, 1996; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Press clippings, 1930-1990; Series 3
  The materials of this series include press clippings concerning Mount Vernon Seminary, Mount Vernon Junior College, and Mount Vernon College. They range in date from 1930-1990.
  - Miscellaneous press clips, 1930-1990; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Press clips, 1975; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Press clips, 1985-1986; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Press clips, 1988-1989; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 8)